Guide to the Wilbur Olin Atwater papers,1869-[ca.1914].
Atwater, Wilbur Olin papers, 1869-[ca.1914].
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Wilbur Olin Atwater papers, 1869-[ca.1914]
2223
Wilbur Olin Atwater, 1844-1907.
39 reels negative microfilm, .7 cubic feet
Letterpress books, correspondence, notes, journals, articles, and pamphlets.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes letterpress books, 1876-1901; incoming letters, 1881-1903; student papers; and notes on experiments. The correspondence is concerned mostly with establishment of experiment stations in the U.S., with chemical analyses carried out, with other professional and administrative duties, and with family affairs. Also, a journal of a trip to Europe in 1869, speeches, articles, and pamphlets.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Wilbur O. Atwater (1844-1907) was an agricultural chemist who was director of the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1875-1877, 1888-1902, and of the Office of Experiment Stations, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1888-1891. He taught chemistry at Wesleyan University from 1873 until his death in 1907.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letterpress books, 1876-1901; incoming letters, 1881-1903; student papers; and notes on experiments. The correspondence is concerned mostly with establishment of experiment stations in the United States, with chemical analyses carried out, with other professional and administrative duties, and with family affairs. Correspondents include American Copyright League, American Chemical Society, American Society for the Extension of University Teaching, Franklin Institute in Philadelphia, Maine State College, New York Association for Improving the Conditions of the Poor, New York Tribune, New York University, Pennsylvania State College, Rose Polytechnic Institute, Simpson College, U.S. Geological Survey, University of Virginia, Yale University, members of Congress, scientific and other periodicals, laboratories, and buinesses. Also, journal of a trip to Europe in 1869, speeches, articles, and pamphlets.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Atwater, Wilbur Olin, 1844-1907.; American Chemical Society.; American Copyright League.; American Society for the Extension of University Teaching.; Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station.; Franklin Institute (Philadelphia, Pa.); Geological Survey (U.S.); Maine State College.; New York Association for Improving the Conditions of the Poor.; New York University.; Pennsylvania State College.; Rose Polytechnic Institute.; Simpson College.
Titles:
New York Tribune.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Connecticut.; Agricultural experiment stations.; Chemistry.; Chemists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Letterpress copybooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Description contains information for collections #2223 and #2793.
CONTAINER LIST
- Notes by Atwater
  - Atwater's handwritten notes (Box 2)
- Publications by Atwater
  - Atwater's publications (Box 1)
- Impression copy books, 1876-1901
  - 1876-1878 (Reel 1)
  - 1878-1884 (Reel 2)
  - 1884-1888 (Reel 3)
  - Mar.-Aug. 1888, Dec. 1886, Jan.-July 1887 (Reel 4)
  - Aug. 1887-Jan. 1889 (Reel 5)
  - Oct. 1890-June 1892 (Reel 6)
  - July 1892-Feb. 1894 (Reel 7)
  - Feb. 1894-Dec. 1894 (Reel 8)
  - Dec. 1894-Apr. 1896 (Reel 9)
  - Apr. 1896-Mar. 1897 (Reel 10)
  - Mar. 1897-Apr. 1898 (Reel 11)
  - Apr. 1898-June 1899 (Reel 12)
  - July 1899-Sept. 1899 (Reel 13)
  - Sept. 1899-June 1900 (Reel 14)
  - June 1900-Dec. 1902 (Reel 15)
  - June 1899-, experiments (Reel 16)
- Incoming correspondence
  - Jan. 1881-Apr. 1884 (Reel 1)
  - May 1884-June 1886 (Reel 2)
  - July 1886-Mar. 1889 (Reel 3)
  - Apr. 1889-Jan. 1891 (Reel 4)
  - Feb. 1891-Dec. 1892 (Reel 5)
  - Jan. 1893-Jan. 1896, no year 1894 (Reel 6)
  - Feb. 1896-Dec. 1897 (Reel 7)
  - Jan. 1898-June 1899 (Reel 8)
  - July 1899-Dec. 1899 (Reel 9)
  - Jan. 1900-Dec. 1900 (Reel 10)
  - Jan. 1901-Nov. 1901 (Reel 11)
  - Dec. 1901-1903 and miscellaneous (Reel 12)
  - Miscellaneous, cont'd (Reel 13)
- Additional W.O. Atwater papers, 1876-1892, accessioned Sept. 13, 1962
  Note: Material not in chronological order. Also, there seems to be material for years 1893, 1894.
  - Papers (Reel 1)
- Additional papers, 1869-1914
  Nine reels negative microfilm made Mar. 1968; originals returned to Wesleyan Univ. Library.
  - Biographical data (Reel 1)
  - Atwater's 1869 journal of trip to Europe (Reel 1)
  - His travel letters and lectures re: Europe printed in the newspapers, 1871-1873 (Reel 1)
  - General correspondence, Feb. 16, 1872-Dec. 16, 1878 (Reel 1)
  - General correspondence, Jan. 6, 1879-May 31, 1887 (Reel 2)
  - General correspondence, June 1, 1887-July 31, 1894 (Reel 3)
  - General correspondence, Aug. 1, 1894-Dec. 22, 1902 (Reel 4)
  - General correspondence, Jan. 2, 1903-1914 and undated (Reel 5)
  - Family correspondence, 1875-1909 and undated (Reel 5)
  - Letterbooks: 1881-May 18, 1885, professional correspondence and reports (Reel 6)
  - Letterbooks: May 19-Aug. 6, 1885, professional correspondence and reports (Reel 7)
  - Letterbooks: 1888-1890, Storrs Agricultural Exper. Station; W.O.A., Director; Chas. D. Woods, Acting Dir. (Reel 7)
  - Speeches and writings: 1897-1904 and undated manuscripts by W.O.A. (includes paper and preparatory notes, 1881-1885 [incollaboration with C.D. Woods] "Nitrogen in Plants"); undated mss. by unspecified authors (Reel 8)
  - Published articles during Atwater's stay at Wesleyan Univ. and others, 1881-1902 (Reel 8)
  - Miscellaneous reports and notes, 1889-ca. 1904 (Reel 8)
  - Experiment Station material (Reel 8)
  - International Nutrition Conference material, 1902 (Reel 8)
  - Food Diet material (Reel 9)
  - Temperance material (Reel 9)